It's a great honor to be here.
انه لشرف كبير أن أتواجد هنا
It's a great honor to be here talking about cities,
انه لشرف كبير أن أتواجد هنا لأتحدث عن المدن
talking about the future of cities.
لأتحدث عن مستقبل المدن
It's great to be here as a mayor.
إنه لشيئ عظيم ان أتواجد كعمدة
I really do believe that mayors have the political position
أنا حقاً اعتقد ان العمد لهم موقع سياسي
to really change people's lives.
لتغيير حياة الناس بالفعل
That's the place to be.
ذلك هو المكان الذي ارغب بالتواجد فيه
And it's great to be here as the mayor of Rio.
و إنه لعظيم ان اكون هنا بصفتي عمدة ريو
Rio's a beautiful city,
فريو مدينة جميلة
a vibrant place, special place.
مكان نابض بالحياة وكذا مكان متميز
Actually, you're looking at a guy
حقيقة ، انتم تنظرون إلى رجل
who has the best job in the world.
لديه أفضل وظيفة
And I really wanted to share with you
وحقيقة وددت أن أشارككم
a very special moment of my life
لحظة مميزة جداً من حياتي
and the history of the city of Rio.
و من تاريخ مدينة ريو
(Video) Announcer: And now, ladies and gentlemen,
(فيديو) المعلن : والآن ، أيها السيدات والسادة
the envelope containing the result.
المظروف الذي يحتوي على النتيجة.
Jacques Rogge: I have the honor to announce
جاك روج: يشرفني أن أعلن
that the games of the 31st Olympiad
أن دورة الالعاب الأوليمبية الواحدة والثلاثون
are awarded to the city of Rio de Janeiro.
قد فازت بها مدينة ريو دي جانيرو
(Cheering)
(تصفيق)
EP: Okay, that's very touching, very emotional,
إ ي بي: حسناً، هذا مؤثر للغاية ، عاطفي جداً
but it was not easy to get there.
ولكنه لم يكن من السهل الوصول إلى هنا
Actually it was a very hard challenge.
في الحقيقة قد كان تحدياً صعباً جداً
We had to beat the European monarchy.
كان يتوجب علينا هزيمة ملكية أوروبا له.
This is Juan Carlos, king of Spain.
هذا هو خوان كارلوس ، ملك إسبانيا
We had to beat the powerful Japanese with all of their technology.
توجب علينا هزيمة اليابانيين الأقوياء مع كل مايمتلكون من تكنولوجيا
We had to beat the most powerful man in the world
توجب علينا هزيمة أقوى إنسان في العالم
defending his own city.
دفاعاً عن مدينته
So it was not easy at all.
لذا لم يكن ذلك سهلاً على الإطلاق
And actually this last guy here said a phrase a few years ago
وفي الواقع فإن آخر شخص هنا قد قال عبارة منذ أعوام قليلة
that I think fits perfectly to the situation
تليق على ما أعتقد على حالة
of Rio winning the Olympic bid.
فوز ريو باحتضان الالعاب الأوليمبية
We really showed that, yes, we can.
لقد أظهرنا في الواقع أننا بالفعل، نستطيع.
And really, this is the reason I came here tonight.
وبالفعل ، هذا هو سبب مجيئي الليلة.
I came here tonight to tell you
لقد جئت الليلة لأخبركم
that things can be done,
أن هذه الاشياء من الممكن أن تتم،
that you don't have always to be rich or powerful
حيث لا يجب أن تكون دوماً غنياً أو قوياً
to get things on the way,
للحصول على الأشياء بالطريقة،
that cities are a great challenge.
التي تتحداك بها هذه المدن
It's a difficult task to deal with cities.
إنه مهمة شاقة في التعامل مع المدن
But with some original ways
ولكن مع بعض الوسائل الأصلية
of getting things done,
لجعل الأشياء تتم
with some basic commandments,
مع بعض الوصايا الاساسية،
you can really get cities
يمكنك بالفعل جعل المدن
to be a great, great place to live.
أن تصبح مكان عظيم للعيش فيه
I want you all to imagine Rio.
أطلب منكم جميعاً تخيل ريو.
You probably think about a city full of energy,
من المحتمل التفكير في مدينة تعج بالطاقة،
a vibrant city full of green.
مدينة تنبض بالحياة ممتلئة بالخضرة
And nobody showed that better
ولم يستطع أحد أن يظهر هذا أحسن من
than Carlos Saldanha in last year's "Rio."
كارلوس سالدانها في ريو العام الماضي
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Video) Bird: This is incredible.
(فيديو) طائر : شيء لايصدق.
EP: Okay, some parts of Rio are pretty much like that,
إي بي : حسناً بعض أجزاء من ريو يشبه هذا الى حد بعيد
but it's not like that everywhere.
ولكنها ليست كذلك في كل مكان
We're like every big city in the world.
فنحن مثل كل المدن الكبيرة في العالم.
We've got lots of people,
لدينا الكثير من الناس،
pollution, cars, concrete, lots of concrete.
تلوث ، سيارات ، أسمنت ، الكثير من الاسمنت.
These pictures I'm showing here,
هذه الصور التي أعرضها هنا،
they are some pictures from Madureira.
هي بعض الصور من ماديوريرا
It's like the heart of the suburb in Rio.
فهي تشبه القلب من ضاحية في ريو
And I want to use an example of Rio
و أنا أود أن أستخدم مثال على ريو
that we're doing in Madureira, in this region,
أن مانفعله في ماديوريرا ، في هذه المنطقة ،
to see what we should think as our first commandment.
لكي نرى ما الذي يتوجب علينا التفكير فيه كوصية أولى
So every time you see a concrete jungle like that,
لذا فكل مرة تشاهد غابة من الاسمنت مثل هذه ،
what you've got to do is find open spaces.
فإن ما يجب عليه فعله هو أن تجد فضاءات مفتوحة.
If you don't have open spaces,
فإذا لم يكن لديك مساحات مفتوحة ،
you've got to go there and open spaces.
فيجب عليك ان تذهب الى هناك وتفتح مساحات.
So go inside these open spaces
وبالتالي إذهب داخل هذه المساحات المفتوحة
and make it that people can get inside
واجعلها صالحة للناس للدخول إليها
and use those spaces.
واستخدام هذه المساحات
This is going to be the third largest park in Rio
ستكون هذه ثالث أكبر متنزه في ريو
by June this year.
في يونيوهذا العام
It's going to be a place where people can meet,
ستكون مكانا حيث يمكن للناس الالتقاء ،
where you can put nature.
حيث يمكنك صناعة طبيعة.
The temperature's going to drop two, three degrees centigrade.
ستنخفض درجات الحرارة درجتان او ثلاثة درجات مئوية
So the first commandment
وبناء عليه فإن أول وصية هي
I want to leave you tonight
أريد أن أترك لكم الليلة
is, a city of the future
مدينة المستقبل
has to be environmentally friendly.
يجب أن تكون صديقة بيئياً
Every time you think of a city,
وكل مرة تفكرون في مدينة ما ،
you've got to think green.
يجب أن تفكرون فيها خضراء
You've got to think green and green.
يجب أن تفكرون فيها خضراء وخضراء
So moving to our second commandment that I wanted to show you.
وبالتالي فإن ثاني وصاياي التي اريد ان اطلعكم عليها هي
Let's think that cities are made of people,
دعونا نفكر ان المدن مصنوعة من الناس
lots of people together.
الكثير من الناس مجتمعة
cities are packed with people.
المدن معبأة بالناس
So how do you move these people around?
إذن كيف تقوم بتحريك هؤلاء الناس ؟
When you have 3.5 billion people living in cities --
عندما يكون لديك ٣،٥ بلايين نسمة يعيشون في مدن --
by 2050, it's going to be 6 billion people.
سيكونون بحلول عام ٢٠٥٠ ستة بلايين نسمة
So every time you think about moving these people around,
إذن عندما تفكر في تحريك هؤلاء الناس
you think about high-capacity transportation.
فإنك تفكر في وسائل مواصلات عالية الكثافة
But there is a problem.
ولكن هناك مشكلة
High-capacity transportation means
فإن المواصلات عالية الكثافة تعني
spending lots and lots of money.
انفاق الكثير والكثير من المال
So what I'm going to show here
ولذلك فإن ما أنا بصدد اطلاعكم عليه هنا
is something that was already presented in TED
هو شيء تم عرضه بالفعل في تيد
by the former mayor of Curitiba
بواسطة العمدة السابق لمدينة كوريتيبا
who created that, a city in Brazil, Jaime Lerner.
والذي ابتكر ذلك ، مدينة في البرازيل ، جيم ليرنر
And it's something that we're doing, again, lots in Rio.
و هو شيئ سنقوم بعمله مرة أخرى بكثرة في ريو
It's the BRT, the Bus Rapid Transit.
ذلك هو ب س ن ، الباص سريع النقل
So you get a bus. It's a simple bus that everybody knows.
إذن ستحصل على باص ، هو باص بسيط يعرفه الجميع
You transform it inside as a train car.
تحوله في الداخل كعربة قطار
You use separate lanes, dedicated lanes.
تستخدم حارات منفصلة ، حارات مخصصة فقط له.
The contractors, they don't like that.
المقاولون ، لن يعجبهم هذا.
You don't have to dig deep down underground.
ليس عليكم ان تحفروا عميقاً تحت الارض
You can build nice stations.
يمكنكم بناء محطات جميلة .
This is actually a station that we're doing in Rio.
هي بالفعل محطة نقوم ببنائها في ريو
Again, you don't have to dig deep down underground
مرة أخرى ، ليس عليكم ان تحفروا عميقا تحت الارض
to make a station like that.
لصنع محطة مثل هذه
This station has the same comfort, the same features
تتمتع المحطة بالراحة ونفس المواصفات
as a subway station.
التي لمحطات مترو الانفاق
A kilometer of this costs a tenth of a subway.
تكلفة الكيلو متر من هذه تساوي عُشر مترو الانفاق
So spending much less money and doing it much faster,
اذن ان تنفق مالاً اقل بكثير وتنجزها أسرع جداً
you can really change the way people move.
يمكنك بالفعل تغيير الطريقة التي يتنقل بها الناس
This is a map of Rio.
هذه خريطة لريو
All the lines, the colored lines you see there,
كل الخطوط ، الخطوط الملونة التي تراها هناك ،
it's our high-capacity transportation network.
هي شبكة النقل عالي الكثافة.
In this present time today,
في الوقت الحالي ، اليوم
we only carry 18 percent of our population
نقوم بحمل ١٨ بالمائة من عدد السكان لدينا
in high-capacity transportation.
بواسطة المواصلات عالية الكثافة
With the BRTs we're doing,
مع النقل العالي الكثافة التي نقوم به،
again, the cheapest and fastest way,
مرة أخرى ، الوسيلة الارخص والاسرع
we're going to move to 63 percent of the population
سوف نتقدم الى نقل ٦٣ بالمائة من عدد السكان
being carried by high-capacity transportation.
الذين يستخدمون النقل العالي الكثافة
So remember what I said:
لذلك تذكروا ماقلته:
You don't always have to be rich or powerful
ليس من الضروري ان تكون غنياً أو قوياً
to get things done.
لانجاز المهام
You can find original ways to get things done.
يمكنك ايجاد الوسائل الاصلية لانجاز المهام
So the second commandment I want to leave you tonight
وبالتالي فان الوصية الثانية التي اود ان اتركها لكم الليلة
is, a city of the future
هي ، مدينة. المستقبل
has to deal with mobility and integration
يجب ان تتعامل مع التحرك والتكامل
of its people.
لشعبها
Moving to the third commandment.
ولننتقل الى الوصية الثالثة
And this is the most controversial one.
و هذه هي الاكثر جدلاً
It has to do with the favelas, the slums --
والتي تخص الاحياء الفقيرة و العشوائيات
whatever you call it, there are different names all over the world.
أياً كان إسمها ، يوجد اسماء مختلفة لها حول العالم
But the point we want to make here tonight
ولكن النقطة التي تود الوصول اليها الليلة
is, favelas are not always a problem.
هي ، الاحياء الفقيرة ليست دائماً مشكلة
I mean, favelas can sometimes
أعني ، احياناً يمكن أن تكون الأحياء الفقيرة
really be a solution,
بالفعل حلاً ،
if you deal with them,
إذا تعاملت معها
if you put public policy inside the favelas.
إذا وضعت سياسية عامة داخل الاحياء الفقيرة
Let me just show a map of Rio again.
دعوني اعرض عليكم خريطة ريو مرة أخرى
Rio has 6.3 million inhabitants --
يقطن ريو ٦.٣ مليون نسمة
More than 20 percent, 1.4 million, live in the favelas.
أكثر من ٢٠ بالمائة ، ١.٤ مليون ، يسكنون احياء فقيرة
All these red parts are favelas.
كل هذه الاجزاء الحمراء هي احياء فقيرة
So you see, they are spread all over the city.
كما ترون ،. فانها تنتشر خلال ارجاء المدينة
This is a typical view of a favela in Rio.
هذا هو منظر نموذجي للاحياء الفقيرة في ريو
You see the contrast between the rich and poor.
سترى التباين بين الغني والفقير
So I want to make two points here tonight about favelas.
لذلك اود ان اشير الى نقطتين هنا هذه الليلة عن الاحياء الفقيرة
The first one is,
الاولى هي
you can change from what I call a [vicious] circle
يمكنك التغيير مما اطلق عليه دائرة الشر
to a virtual circle.
الى الدائرة الافتراضية
But what you've got to do to get that
ولكن ما يتوجب عليك فعله للحصول على ذلك
is you've got to go inside the favelas,
هو انه يجب عليك الذهاب الى داخل الاحياء الفقيرة
bring in the basic services --
تزويدهم بالخدمات الاساسية
mainly education and health -- with high quality.
التعليم والصحة في المقام الاول -- بجودة عالية
I'm going to give a fast example here.
سوف أعطيكم مثال سريع على ذلك هنا
This was an old building in a favela in Rio --
هذا كان مبنىً قديماً في حي فقير في ريو --
[unclear favela name] --
[اسم الحي الفقير غير واضح]--
that we just transformed into a primary school,
والذي حولناه للتو الى مدرسة ابتدائية،
with high quality.
بجودة عالية
This is primary assistance in health
هذه مساعدة اولية في الصحة
that we built inside a favela,
التي بنيناها في الحي الفقير
again, with high quality.
مرة اخرى بجودة عالية
We call it a family clinic.
وأسميناها عيادة الأسرة
So the first point is bring basic services
إذن فأول نقطة هي جلب الخدمات الاساسية
inside the favelas
الى داخل الحي الفقير
with high quality.
بجودة عالية
The second point I want to make about the favelas
والنقطة الثانية التي اود توضيحها عن الاحياء الفقيرة
is, you've got to open spaces in the favela.
هي انه يجب ان تفتح مساحات في الاحياء الفقيرة
Bring infrastructure
جلب البنية التحتية
to the favelas, to the slums, wherever you are.
الى الاحياء الفقيرة ، الى العشوائيات ، اينما تكون.
Rio has the aim, by 2020,
ان ريو لديها هدف انه بحلول عام ٢٠٢٠،
to have all its favelas completely urbanized.
هو تحويل كل احيائها الفقيرة الى اماكن حضرية
Another example, this was completely packed with houses,
مثال آخر، وهو معبأ تماماً بالمنازل
and then we built this, what we call, a knowledge square.
ومن ثم بنينا هذا ، مااطلقنا عليه اسم ، مربع المعرفة
This is a place with high technology
هذا مكان مزود بتقنية عالية
where the kids that live in a poor house next to this place
حيث يقطن الاطفال في منزل فقير بالقرب من هذا المكان
can go inside and have access to all technology.
يمكنهم الذهاب اليه والدخول الى كل التقنيات
We even built a theater there -- 3D movie.
حتى اننا بنبنا سينما هناك - افلام ثلاثية الابعاد
And this is the kind of change you can get for that.
وهذا هو نوع التغيير الذي يمكنك الحصول عليه لهذ الغرض
And by the end of the day you get something better than a TED Prize,
وفي نهاية اليوم ستحصل على شيئ افضل من جائزة تيد
which is this great laugh
ألا و هي ضحكة كبيرة
from a kid that lives in the favela.
من طفل يعيش في حي فقير
So the third commandment I want to leave here tonight
وبالتالي فان الوصية الثالثة التي اريد ان اودعها اياكم الليلة
is, a city of the future
هي مدينة المستقبل
has to be socially integrated.
يجب ان تكون متكاملة مجتمعياً
You cannot deal with a city
لا يمكنك التعامل مع مدينة
if it's not socially integrated.
اذا لم تكن متكاملة مجتمعياً
But moving to our fourth commandment,
ولكن بالانتقال الى وصيتنا الرابعة
I really wouldn't be here tonight.
فلن اكون متواجدا هنا الليلة
Between November and May, Rio's completely packed.
مابين نوفمبر ومايو ستكون ريو مكتظة بالكامل
We just had last week Carnivale.
لقد كان لدينا الاسبوع الماضي كرنفال
It was great. It was lots of fun.
لقد كان عظيماً به الكثير من المتعة
We have New Year's Eve.
لدينا حواء نيويورك
There's like two million people on Copacabana Beach.
هناك حوالي مليونان من البشر على شاطئ كوباكابانا
We have problems.
لدينا مشاكل
We fight floods, tropical rains at this time of the year.
نحارب الفيضانات ، الامطار الاستوائية في هذا الوقت من العام.
You can imagine how people get happy with me
يمكنكم تخيل مدى سعادة الناس معي
watching these kinds of scenes.
وهم يشاهدون هذا النوع من المشاهد
We have problems with the tropical rains.
لدينا مشاكل مع الامطار الاستوائية
Almost every year
تقريباً كل عام
we have these landslides, which are terrible.
لدينا هذه الانزلاقات الارضية والتي تعتبر مرعبة
But the reason I could come here
ولكن السبب الذي اتى بي هنا
is because of that.
هو لهذا السبب
This was something we did with IBM
هذا شيئٌ انجزناه مع اي بي ام
that's a little bit more than a year old.
تقريبا منذ اكثر من عام
It's what we call the Operations Center of Rio.
وهو ما نطلق عليه مركز عمليات ريو
And I wanted to show that I can govern my city, using technology,
واود ان اعرض انني استطيع ادارة مدينتي باستخدام التكنولوجيا
from here, from Long Beach,
من هنا ، من لونج بييتش
so I got here last night and I know everything.
وبالتالي فقد حضرت هنا الليلة الماضية واعلم كل شيئ
We're going to speak now to the Operations Center.
سنتحدث الآن إلى مركز العمليات
This is Osorio,
هذا هو أوسوريو
he's our secretary of urban affairs.
وهو سكرتيرنا لشئون الحضر
So Osorio, good to be there with you.
اذن اوسوريو ، جميل ان نكون هناك معك
I've already told the people
لقد اخبرت الناس بالفعل
that we have tropical rain this time of year.
اننا لدينا امطاراً استوائية هذا العام
So how's the weather in Rio now?
اذن كيف هو حال الطقس الآن في ريو
Osorio: The weather is fine. We have fair weather today.
اوسوريو: الطقس جيد لدينا طقس صحو اليوم
Let me get you our weather satellite radar.
دعني اريك رادار الطقس الخاص بنا
You see just a little bit of moisture around the city.
ترى هنا كمية ضئيلة نوعا من الرطوبة حول المدينة
Absolutely no problem in the city in terms of weather,
بالطبع لا توجد مشكلة بالنسبة للطقس
today and in the next few days.
اليوم والايام القليلة المقبلة
EP: Okay, how's the traffic?
اي بي: حسناً كيف حال الموصلات
We, at this time of year, get lots of traffic jams.
نحن نعاني في هذا الوقت من العام الكثير من اللاختناقات المرورية
People get mad at the mayor. So how's the traffic tonight?
والناس تستشيط غضباً على العمدة . اذن كيف حال المرور الليلة ؟
Osario: Well traffic tonight is fine.
اوساريو: حسناً المرور الليلة جيد
Let me get you one of our 8,000 buses.
دعني اريك احد باصاتنا ال٨٠٠٠
A live transmission in downtown Rio for you, Mr. Mayor.
بث مباشر من وسط المدينة لك سيدي العمدة
You see, the streets are clear.
ترى الشوارع خالية
Now it's 11:00 pm in Rio.
الآن الساعة ١١:٠٠ مساءً في ريو
Nothing of concern in terms of traffic.
لاشيئ يدعو للاهتمام بالنسبة للمرور
I'll get to you now the incidents of the day.
سأحضرك لك الآن احداث اليوم
We had heavy traffic early in the morning
كان لدينا اختناق مروري في الصباح
and in the rush hour in the afternoon,
وفي ساعة الذروة بعد الظهر
but nothing of big concern.
ولكن ليس بالاهتمام الكبير
We are below average
نحن تحت المتوسط
in terms of traffic incidents in the city.
بالنسبة لحوادث المرور في المدينة
EP: Okay, so you're showing now some public services.
اي بي: حسناً اذن انت تعرض لنا بعض الخدمات العامة
These are the cars.
هذه هي السيارات
Osorio: Absolutely, Mr. Mayor.
اوسوريو: بالطبع سيدي العمدة
Let me get you the fleet of our waste collection trucks.
دعني اريك اسطول شاحنات جمع القمامة
This is live transmission.
هذا بث مباشر
We have GPS's in all of our trucks.
لدينا جهاز تحديد المواقع في جميع شاحناتنا
And you can see them working
ويمكنك مشاهدتها تعمل
in all parts of the city.
في كل جزء من المدينة
Waste collection on time.
جمع القمامة في الموعد المحدد
Public services working well.
الخدمات العامة تعمل بكفاءة
EP: Okay, Osorio, thank you very much.
اي بي: حسناً ، اوسوريو شكراً جزيلاً لك
It was great to have you here.
قد كان عظيما. تواجدك معنا هنا
We're going to move so that I can make a conclusion.
سنمضي قدماً لذا استطيع ان انتقل الى المحصلة النهائية
(Applause)
تصفيق
Okay, so no files, this place, no paperwork,
حسناً: لاتوجدملفات ، هذا المكان ، لايوجد عمل ورقي
no distance, 24/7 working.
لامسافات، ٧/٢٤ عمل
So the fourth commandment I want to share with you here tonight
اذن الوصية الرابعة التي اريد مشاركتكم اياها الليلة
is, a city of the future
هي مدينة المستقبل
has to use technology to be present.
يجب ان تستخدم التكنولوجيا لتكون متواجدة
I don't need to be there anymore to know and to administrate the city.
لا اريد ان اكون هناك بعد الان لاعرف ولا لأديرالمدينة
But everything that I said here tonight, or the commandments,
ولكن اي شيئ قلته هنا الليلة أو الوصايا
are means, are ways,
هي وسائل هي طرق
for us to govern cities --
لنا للتحكم في المدن
invest in infrastructure, invest in the green,
استثمر في البنية التحتية ، استثمر في الخضرة
open parks, open spaces,
افتح متنزهات افتح مساحات
integrate socially, use technology.
تكامل مجتمعياً ، استخدم التكنولوجيا
But at the end of the day, when we talk about cities,
ولكن في نهاية اليوم عندما نتكلم عن المدن
we talk about a gathering of people.
نحن نتكلم عن تجميع الناس
And we cannot see that as a problem.
و لا يمكن ان نرى هذه على انها مشكلة
That is fantastic.
هذا بديع
If there's 3.5 billion now,
لو كان هناك ٣.٥ بليون الأن
it's going to be six billion then it's going to be 10 billion.
سوف تصبح ستة بلايين آنئذ وسوف تصبح ١٠ بلايين
That is great, that means we're going to have
هذا عظيم . هذا يعني انه سيكون لدينا
10 billion minds working together,
١٠ بلايين عقل يعملون معاً
10 billion talents together.
١٠ بلايين موهبة مجتمعة
So a city of the future,
اذن فمدينة المستقبل
I really do believe
إنني اعتقد اعتقاداً جازماً
that it's a city that cares about its citizens,
أنها المدينة التي تهتم بالمواطنين
integrates socially its citizens.
تتكامل مجتمعياً مع مواطنيها
A city of the future is a city that can never let anyone out
مدينة المستقبل هي مدينة لا تخذل أحداً
of this great party, which are cities.
من هذا الطرف العظيم ، وهو المدن
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً
(Applause)
تصفيق